<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3b2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>

  <title>Motivation</title>

  <para>Every user of eComStation or OS/2 knows that: When people see 
  your desktop, they usually ask what kind of Linux you are running. If 
  you explain to them that it has nothing to do with Linux and that the 
  original system was done by IBM and they called it OS/2, we either 
  end up with a big question mark on their face or with a statement 
  like <quote>Oh, I used to work with that as well, it was good but I 
  didn&apos;t have any software/drivers/whatever for it.</quote> People 
  who have worked with it a bit more explain that it was the best thing 
  to administrate their fileservers, if they were even more skilled 
  they start telling stories about how they did interact with the 
  desktop and you can still see a twinkle in their eyes when they talk 
  about it. The authors of this book are still using OS/2 or its 
  official successor eComStation every day. We work on it, we write 
  software for it, we extend it. But we are realistic. We know that one 
  day there will not be any more hardware to run it on, at least not in 
  native mode. We know that already nowadays we have to invest a lot of 
  time, money, and energy to get things like ACPI done, and to port 
  de-facto standards like OpenOffice and the Mozilla suite to it. We 
  also know that we will never get the source code of the system by 
  IBM, the thing we would desperately need to fix some very annoying 
  bugs and limitations it has.</para>

  <para>So we have to think about the options we have. Some of us have 
  done that over the past years and some of us came up with more or 
  less detailed ideas of how this could be done. Some of the ideas were 
  simply not realistic but we finally think that we have found a good 
  concept by now. A concept that provides all the things we love about 
  OS/2, PM, and the WPS but also a concept that solves the limitations 
  and restrictions of our current system, a concept that has a future. 
  This is what this book is about.</para>

  <section>

    <title>Facts and Religion</title>

    <para>In <xref linkend="dov.overview.tvp.h"/> we explain the 
    history of the Voyager project, including some details of what IBM 
    planned to do with OS/2 years ago. As we all know, things went 
    differently. OS/2 never met the success it deserved from a 
    technical point of view and the world is still dominated by 
    Microsoft and Windows.</para>

    <para>After the first presentation of Voyager to the public at 
    Warpstock Europe 2006, we got a lot of feedback about the idea, 
    both positive and negative. There were people who got the idea of 
    Voyager right from the beginning, they understood that we do not 
    want to take OS/2 away from anyone, nor give up development of new 
    features for eComStation or anything. But still, the negative 
    feedback was there, some people absolutely didn&apos;t want to 
    understand why Voyager is necessary and why people should invest 
    time into it. So before we go into the glory details let me explain 
    why we think Voyager is necessary from our point of view. To 
    explain that we go more that 10 years back in time, and we get a 
    bit more personal than in the other chapters.</para>

    <section>

      <title>The Reason for OS/2</title>

      <para>The author of these lines was using Windows 3.1 until some 
      time in 1994. After a lot of system breakdowns on a rainy 
      Saturday evening, I decided that it could not go on like that 
      anymore. I went to my neighbour who was working at IBM and I told 
      him <quote>Get me this operating system from IBM.</quote> I 
      didn&apos;t know the name and I didn&apos;t know what it was 
      about, I had just heard that it was more stable than Windows and 
      that was tempting enough for me. A few weeks later I got a brand 
      new box of OS/2 Warp 3, went home, and installed it. I started 
      the desktop and shut down the system shortly afterwards. I had no 
      idea what I was supposed to do with that system at that 
      point.</para>

      <para>It took me a few weeks to get used to it. I got software 
      for the new system from German magazines which came with a lot of 
      shareware and freeware. OS/2 was pretty popular in Germany back 
      then, so there was a market for that. I never used the included 
      Windows support a lot, the only application I wanted to run did 
      not work because it was a MIDI sequencer which required support 
      for sound cards that were not supported on OS/2. But I still 
      liked it. It was stable, it was innovative, it was different. And 
      I learned that, from a technical point of view, it was far 
      superior to any Windows, including the upcoming Windows 95.</para>

      <para>The following years I went through my advocacy phase where 
      I tried to explain why I was using OS/2 to everyone, why 
      <emphasis>they</emphasis> should use OS/2, and why Windows sucked 
      and Microsoft was evil. I didn&apos;t have much success because 
      for most friends it was more important to be able to play the 
      latest games and get drivers for about every hardware they could 
      buy for money. They lived with the fact that the system was not 
      stable or that they had to reinstall it from scratch every few 
      months. Recently, one of those friends told me that they were 
      very jealous back then when I took my OS/2 machine to a demoscene 
      event because I was the only one in there who could play Quake 
      and burn a CD at the same time without the system crashing. So, 
      at least for a little moment, I had my fame with OS/2.</para>

      <para>My advocacy phase has been over for a long time, meanwhile 
      I&apos;ve started a project called netlabs.org and I&apos;ve met 
      a lot of great people from all over the world with the same 
      spirit: The idea that there is more out there than Windows, 
      MacOS, Linux, or any of the other operating systems. The 
      knowledge that IBM <emphasis>did</emphasis> do some things right, 
      even if that neither included marketing nor the technical 
      implementation of some of the concepts they designed. I still use 
      OS/2 every day, even if I work with many of the Unix-like 
      operating systems out there every day to earn my living.</para>

      <tip>

        <title>netlabs.org</title>

        <para>netlabs.org was founded in 1997 with the goal of creating 
        a center for free Open Source Software for OS/2 and also 
        eComStation (eCS). Today, netlabs.org is one of the largest 
        developers of OS/2 software outside of IBM itself.</para>

        <para>With its many ground-breaking projects, netlabs.org has 
        won a name for itself in the great OS/2 and eCS Community. More 
        information and projects can be found at 
        <ulink url="http://www.netlabs.org/">
        http://www.netlabs.org/</ulink>.</para>

      </tip>

      <para>You might ask why I write that in a book about Voyager. The 
      reason is pretty simple: Every OS/2 user had a story of his own 
      about how he or she started using it. I bet that for most people 
      it had something to do with technical reasons, because you 
      <emphasis>knew</emphasis> that it was better. So what was your 
      motivation back then? Think about that again before you read the 
      next sections.</para>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>The Reason for eComStation</title>

      <para>While IBM was investing less and less time into the 
      development of OS/2, a group of people at Serenity Systems 
      International (SSI) managed to get a license from IBM to 
      distribute the core of OS/2 under a new name and extend it with 
      new software. The final product is now called eComStation and by 
      now it has become the only legal way to get an OS/2-like 
      operating system, especially since IBM stopped selling OS/2 in 
      January 2006.</para>

      <para>When eComStation 1.0 got released in 2001 IBM was still 
      selling OS/2 but many OS/2 users switched to eComStation. The 
      reason was pretty simple: eCS included a lot of things in the 
      default installation that users of OS/2 installed anyway—and much 
      more. It was no longer necessary to patch a freshly installed 
      system with the latest fixpacks right away and install software 
      like <application>WarpIN</application>, <application>
      XWorkplace</application>, <application>Mozilla</application>, and 
      all the other applications.</para>

      <para>Meanwhile OS/2 does not exist anymore, eCS is the only way 
      to get the <quote>OS/2 feeling</quote> on your desktop and you 
      get much more with it. SSI is currently working on eComStation 
      2.0, which will add more important features and which also shows 
      a clear trend: Use industry standards that are available as open 
      source software and integrate them into the WPS. Examples of this 
      are <application>OpenOffice.org 2.0</application>, <application>
      Samba</application>, <application>CDRecord</application>, and 
      much more.</para>

    </section>

    <section>

      <title>The Reason for Voyager</title>

      <para>As described above, eComStation made it possible for the 
      first time to add things to our operating system that IBM had 
      refused to include all the years before. This is a great thing 
      because it is now possible to extend and adjust the system to our 
      needs.</para>

      <para>However, over the past months it also became clear that the 
      current kernel of eComStation will reach its design limits one 
      day. While we still can get it to work on recent hardware due to 
      extensions like ACPI support, things might change in the future. 
      The trend nowadays is clearly 64 bit platforms and even if it 
      will take some months or even years until they are used 
      everywhere, we cannot use new features of such CPUs and 
      mainboards with the current kernel.</para>

      <para>Another issue is the time needed to develop new features 
      like ACPI. After years of running a project like netlabs.org we 
      are simply tired of writing device drivers for new hardware and 
      trying to circumvent limitations in the current kernel to get 
      something to work. This is very boring work and it does not lead 
      anywhere because new hardware is released every day. So instead 
      of focusing on interesting work like integrating applications 
      into the Workplace Shell, we lose time on moving targets.</para>

      <tip>

        <title>Workplace Shell (WPS)</title>

        <para>The Workplace Shell (WPS) is an award-winning 
        object-oriented desktop shell produced by IBM&apos;s Boca Raton 
        development lab for OS/2 2.0. It is based on Common User Access 
        and made a radical shift away from the Program Manager type 
        interface that earlier versions of OS/2 shared with Windows 3.x 
        or the application-oriented WIMP interface of the Apple 
        Macintosh. The Workplace Shell was also used in OS/2 Warp 3 and 
        Warp 4 (now abandoned by IBM), and is still the user interface 
        of the revamped successor to OS/2 called eComStation. Source: 
        <ulink url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Workplace_Shell"/>
        </para>

      </tip>

      <para>The same issue exists with GUI-based applications like 
      <application>Mozilla</application> and <application>
      OpenOffice.org</application>. They always rely on a GUI Toolkit. 
      Popular toolkits nowadays are GTK+, qt, wxWidgets, and SWT. We 
      spent and still spend quite some time on getting those toolkits 
      to work on OS/2 PM. This also is a never-ending work because they 
      get extended on a regular base as well. Again, we loose time on 
      things that are of no immediate benefit, they are just required 
      to get the application itself to OS/2. This costs both a lot of 
      time and money, because we have to pay developers to port those 
      toolkits. Otherwise they never would get finished in a reasonable 
      time.</para>

      <para>Earlier in the book we asked you about your motivation to 
      use OS/2 back then. We hope you could remember the motivation and 
      we also hope that it had something to do with the technical 
      benefits of OS/2. If you are sceptic against the idea of Voyager 
      answer yourself the following questions:</para>

      <itemizedlist>

        <listitem>

          <para>Are the arguments for OS/2 still valid nowadays from a 
          technical point of view?</para>

        </listitem>

        <listitem>

          <para>Would you still choose OS/2 if you wouldn&apos;t care 
          about unique concepts like the WPS?</para>

        </listitem>

      </itemizedlist>

      <para>For sure there is more to OS/2 and eCS than just the WPS, 
      we will talk about that later. But in our opinion those concepts 
      are not necessarily bound to OS/2 as a kernel and operating 
      system. And that is exactly what Voyager is about: 
      <emphasis>Implement the unique concepts as open source software 
      for eCS and for other platforms!</emphasis></para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section>

    <title>Conclusion</title>

    <para>There are many things in OS/2 that are worth keeping but it 
    would not make sense to clone the current OS as a whole. The 
    community could never do that and even if we could, it 
    wouldn&apos;t solve the problems we are suffering from 
    nowadays.</para>

    <para>Based on the arguments mentioned before we can come up with a 
    list of things that would be nice to have in a perfect 
    environment:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>

        <para>The system provides a stable kernel with a decent device 
        driver subsystem.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>All recent GUI toolkits are provided by the system, 
        without porting or maintenance work for us.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Hardware is just there to do a job for us. We do not care 
        about device drivers, they are provided by the base 
        system.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>De-facto standards can easily be compiled. Patching of 
        application source code is not required.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Our programmers implement a WPS-like environment on top 
        of this system.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Applications are perfectly integrated into this WPS-like 
        desktop.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>And in a really perfect world we even get our legacy OS/2 
        and eCS applications to work.</para>

      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

    <para>A project like Voyager needs to focus on its main idea, 
    everything that distracts from that goal should be reconsidered 
    and, if possible, be replaced by something existing. In the next 
    chapters, we will explain in detail in the next chapters which core 
    components need to be written by ourself and which components can 
    be taken from other projects. We believe that this approach makes 
    it possible to make Voyager a real piece of software instead of 
    vaporware or a nice design study as it is at the time 
    writing.</para>

    <para>It would not make sense to make any statement about how fast 
    this can be implemented and about how many of the mentioned things 
    will be reached within the next months and years. But if we do not 
    try, we will never find out.</para>

  </section>

  <para />

  <para />

  <para />

</chapter>

