<?xml version='1.0'?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.3b2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="dov.contrib">

  <title>Contributing to Voyager</title>

  <para>As you can see this book is far away from being complete. Also, 
  there is not that much source code available yet for Voyager so we 
  need any support we can get to go on with this project. This project 
  is a big undertaking and it will need months of work before we will 
  get first results. But every project starts out small and if we do 
  not try it, we will never know if we can succeed with it.</para>

  <para>It is important that people start supporting Voyager right from 
  the beginning. After all we design Voyager not just for us, but also 
  for you. This part of the book will show you how 
  <emphasis>you</emphasis> can contribute to Voyager.</para>

  <section id="dov.contrib.d">

    <title>Developers</title>

    <para>Probably the best case right now for Voyager would be if you 
    are a developer that likes the idea and wants to contribute. If 
    this is the case for you, welcome on board! As you could see 
    Voyager consists of quite some parts, some of them are more, some 
    less defined so far. It doesn&apos;t matter on which part you want 
    to work, we are open to any contributions. Note that some parts 
    already have a lead developer and we might be quite picky about 
    technical details. So we hope we can have some positive discussions 
    and later also contributions from your side.</para>

    <para>It is not just coding that needs help from developers, right 
    now there are many open questions and maybe you have a lot of know 
    how about kernel design. So you could for example contribute to the 
    kernel chapter in this book to make sure that we get more details 
    in there. It is up to you, feel free to contact us on any of the 
    ways mentioned here.</para>

    <para>Please introduce yourself quickly when you join IRC or the 
    mailing-list. Don&apos;t give up if no one gives an answer right 
    away, we live in different timezones and we have daytime jobs, so 
    it is not always easy to find the time needed for an answer.</para>

    <section id="dov.contrib.d.i">

      <title>IRC</title>

      <para>Some of the core developers of Voyager are online in IRC on 
      a regular base, you will find us in the <computeroutput>
      #netlabs</computeroutput> channel on <command>
      irc.netlabs.org</command>. You will get a list of other servers 
      when you connect to it.</para>

    </section>

    <section id="dov.contrib.d.m">

      <title>Mailing-lists/Newsgroups</title>

      <para>netlabs.org provides mailing-lists as well, there is a 
      specific Voyager mailinglist called <computeroutput>
      voyager-dev@netlabs.org</computeroutput>. To subscribe to it send 
      an email to <computeroutput>
      voyager-dev-subscribe@netlabs.org</computeroutput>, you will get 
      a confirmation email shortly afterwards.</para>

      <para>If you do not like mailing-lists you can use a web/news 
      (nntp) interace as well. This is provided by gmane.org, a 
      mail-to-news and vice versa gateway. The Voyager mailinglist can 
      be found here: <ulink url="http://dir.gmane.org/"/></para>

    </section>

    <section id="dov.contrib.d.gs">

      <title>Getting the Source</title>

      <para>Souce code of Voyager is managed in a Subversion repository 
      at netlabs.org. We also provide TRAC for managing the projects. 
      You can get more information about that at 
      <ulink url="http://svn.netlabs.org/voyager"/>.</para>

      <para>Please check this page as well for instructions about 
      Subversion. The structure of the Voyager repository is a bit 
      complex, the most recent information about how to get it can be 
      found in TRAC as well.</para>

    </section>

  </section>

  <section id="dov.contrib.u">

    <title>Users</title>

    <para>Users can contribute to Voyager right now as well. While 
    there is nothing to test yet and probably won&apos;t be for the 
    next months, it is important that people know Voyager right from 
    the beginning. As mentioned in this book, there seems to be a big 
    confusion among users about what Voyager is, or will be. Also, many 
    people think that netlabs.org will now stop developing for eCS and 
    OS/2. Again, this is absolutely not the case and you can help us if 
    you talk to users about that and explain the idea of Voyager. The 
    worst thing that could happen would be when the already small OS/2 
    and eCS community splitted up into two parts. So help us doing 
    Voyager advocacy but also listen to the arguments and fears of 
    people who do not understand or like the idea of Voyager yet. It is 
    important that we take them seriously and try to show them that 
    their arguments are not valid. Even sceptical people might come up 
    with great ideas we did not think of. If this is the case, let us 
    know. See <xref linkend="dov.contrib.d"/> about how to get in touch 
    with us.</para>

    <para>There are a few more things you can do for Voyager:</para>

    <itemizedlist>

      <listitem>

        <para>Present Voyager to your local usergroup, distribute this 
        book to people, and show presentations available at 
        netlabs.org. The Developers Workshop presentation is also 
        available as Ogg-file so you could listen to it to get some 
        more details.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Correct the text in this book. Most authors right now are 
        not native English speakers so it might sound a bit rough. See 
        <xref linkend="dov.appb.c"/> for more information about 
        that.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>CUA (FIXME)</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Try to bring Voyager into the news, write articles about 
        it if you have contacts. We need to attract more people and 
        getting news coverage might help a lot about that.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Try to find sponsors for Voyager, see 
        <xref linkend="dov.contrib.s"/>.</para>

      </listitem>

      <listitem>

        <para>Help us translating Voyager, see 
        <xref linkend="dov.contrib.t"/>.</para>

      </listitem>

    </itemizedlist>

  </section>

  <section id="dov.contrib.t">

    <title>Translators</title>

    <para>Explain where to get the strings to translate, explain how 
    one can get Subversion commiter for a language, etc.</para>

    <para>It is a bit too early for that, will be described as soon as 
    it is ready.</para>

  </section>

  <section id="dov.contrib.s">

    <title>Sponsoring/Fund Raising</title>

    <para>As you can imagine, Voyager is a very big project. So far all 
    programmers working on Voyager do this for free in their 
    spare-time. While this works for quite some open source project, it 
    is also a fact that almost all big successful projects do have 
    fulltime programmers working on them. The benefit is quite obvious: 
    There is a difference if one can workon a project 8 hours a day, 5 
    days a week or just a few hours a week or in best case a few hours 
    a day. Projects like OpenOffice.org, Mozilla but also Gnome and KDE 
    do have fulltime programmers.</para>

    <para>netlabs.org already hires developers, on project or permanent 
    base. So far the development was payed with sponsoring from users 
    and companies, and if there was not enough money, the founder of 
    netlabs.org, Adrian Gschwend, payed the difference on his own. 
    During the last three years Adrian Gschwend invested around 
    20&apos;000 Euro of his very own money into netlabs.org.</para>

    <para>While this was ok for the last three years he has to change 
    that now. netlabs.org should get self-supporting.</para>

  </section>

</chapter>

